Some breaking news on the campus of the University of Chicago. Campus police
they're breaking up a protester encampment. Police in riot gear arrived on campus
early this morning. Joni has been there very early. She has the latest. Joni, what
has unfolded since you arrived? Well, the campus police, as you said, moved in just
before 5 a.m. and these protesters have been holding the line now for two hours.
There's a bullhorn behind us, so it's very loud. Christopher was on the inside when
it happened. Describe what happened in the quadrangle this morning. Yeah, it was
horrific. They waited like cowards until every single student was asleep in their
tent, basically. And then they stormed in, maybe 40 or 50 of them, with riot gear
screaming. They started throwing wood planks, throwing chairs, throwing
absolutely everything in any direction to destroy the camp as fast as possible, to
suppress this movement as fast as possible. And in fact, one of the chairs that they
threw came within maybe three inches of hitting my girlfriend in the head. And
they had just woken us up. It was dark. I tried to make sure everyone was safe. I mean,
it was chaos. It was terrifying. Yeah. They gave us some ridiculous notice out here saying
that, like, participants in the quad encampment, which no longer exists, thanks to
them, are facing, like, an interim leave of absence, as well as a criminal trespass
charge. I have no idea if that's just a scare tactic or if it's real, but it doesn't matter
because the difference between us and people like these cops is that there are limits to
when we continue following orders. And when you're talking about a genocide visited upon
a colonized population of two million people trapped in a ghetto that's as long as a marathon
and six miles wide, when that ghetto is being systematically starved, slaughtered, every
hospital bombed, every university bombed, 70 percent of homes destroyed, 40,000 people
murdered, 15,000 children murdered, the entire population on the brink of starvation. We say,
and if our government and our academic institutions are complicit in this, there comes a point where
we say we're not following orders and it doesn't matter what you do to us because there are principles
and there are human lives that matter more than our careers and our futures. And that's what
separates us from people like Paul Alivisato is the coward president of this university
and these coward cops that come in terrorizing and encampment while people are sleeping.
You've been standing in this line linked arm in arm with other protesters. What has happened
here? What's happening here? You'd have to ask them. Apparently they're trying to intimidate
us, trying to suppress the protests that is continuing to grow. I think that they thought
they could basically terrify us into inaction, into flight. But this is what this university
has never understood, has never accepted, has never reckoned with about this student movement,
and not just at UChicago but around the country, is that the commitment to Gaza runs deeper than
fears for our safety, fears for our careers, fears for our paychecks. It is a fundamental obligation
we have as citizens of a country that is presiding over this genocide, arming this genocide, and
as students at a university that is invested in those same weapons manufacturers and that
is partnered with the same apartheid institutions that train that military and develop its technology.
There was some pushing. I don't know who was pushing or shoving, but I know that there was tension here at the line.
You've tried to have a conversation with some of these police officers.
Yeah, I've been talking to them this whole time. I've been asking them what it would take for them to stop following orders.
I would ask them, you know, how many kids have to die? So if you say 15,000 kids are killed,
they're still willing to violently suppress a national movement raising the alarm that this needs to stop,
that the U.S. complicity needs to stop. So what if it was 50,000 kids, 200,000 kids, a million kids?
What if the whole Gaza ghetto...
Do you know if there are next steps here?
For them?
Yeah.
For me, the next step is a simple one, whatever form it takes, which is to continue fighting with every breath we have,
with everything we have, for the people of Gaza, because the blood of those kids is on our hands.
It's on all of our hands, whether we like it or not. If we're U.S. citizens, if we're UChicago students,
we are implicated in this horror that is being visited with total impunity because of U.S. Security Council vetoes by the state of Israel.
Are you a student?
I'm a student. Yes, I'm a Ph.D. student.
And if you face discipline, what's that?
Again, I don't care. It doesn't matter. There are things that matter more than my academic future.
And certainly every one of those children that is being murdered, starved, maimed, whose parents are having to choose,
you know, do I let this kid starve first or that one?
And this is such an ugly reality of such great magnitude that to even think, to really entertain questions about, like,
oh, what might happen if Paul puts me on a leave of absence is ridiculous.
And it's insulting to the memory of every child that has been murdered in the course of this genocide
with the full complicity of the United States, of Joe Biden, and of people like Paul Alivisatos and his cops
that he sticks on us in the middle of the night.
They're hypocrites, they're cowards, and the blood of Gaza's kids is on their hands, too.
The difference between them and us is that we know that and we reckon with it
because we have a duty to them while they hide from the truth,
and they won't even admit that a single university has been bombed.
We know that because it doesn't mean that they're unable to claim.
We know that we're not going to be able to claim that we're going to be able to claim that we can't take that
long term résultats, and we're going to claim that we can't limit it.
And we know that we've been making decisions about this.
We're still waiting for this to keep our clients all over time.
And we're not ready for this to keep our clients.
It's gonna be a few more questions about, though.
So, if we can do this to keep our clients and keep our clients coming into the future,
but when they're going back to the team, then we're going to go home more.